嗨，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的游戏引擎系列，上期讨论了渲染器接口抽象
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my game engine series, so last time we took a look at renderer api abstraction
如果你们还没看过，就去看看那期视频吧，基本上只是把一堆代码抽到渲染接口对应的类
check out that video, if you haven't already, we basically just pulled out a bunch of our code into specific classes that were kind of per render api
那么我们现在在处理的是OpenGL，所以创建了OpenGLVertexBuffer和OpenGLIndexBuffer类
so we're dealing with OpenGL at the moment, so we created like an OpenGLVertexBuffer and OpenGLIndexBuffer class
那是专门用来处理那些渲染接口的，比如图元之类的东西
there was specifically for dealing with those kind of render api, like primitives or just things essentially
在某种程度上，当我们从应用程序或游戏代码或渲染器代码中调用时，它就被抽象出来了
in a way that was kind of abstracted out where, when we kind of call it from our application, or from our game kind of code, or from our renderer code
它并不关心底层实际使用的是哪个接口，所以如果还没有看过的话，一定要看看那期视频
it doesn't care which api is actually used under the hood, so definitely check out that video, if you haven't already
今天我们会继续往下讲，但我们会特别讲缓冲区布局
we're gonna kind of continue down that slope today, but we're specifically going to talk about buffer layouts
当我说缓冲区布局时，我指的是顶点缓冲区布局，对吧，已经接触过这个了
and when I say buffer layouts, I mean I'm really talking about vertex buffer layouts, okay, we touched on this
我的意思是，我们在我的频道上已经大体谈到了这个
I mean we've touched on this on my channel just in general
因为如果不处理顶点缓冲布局的话，你们就无法渲染任何东西
because of course you can't really render anything without having to deal with vertex buffer layouts
我想我在OpenGL的系列中有一个专门的视频，我会试着把它链接起来
I think I have a video specifically about that in the OpenGL story, so I'll try and link it up there
如果你们还没有看过的话，一定要去看看，一般来说，如果你们不熟悉OpenGL系列的话
definitely check that out, if you haven't already, and in general, if you're not familiar with the OpenGL stories
我只会看一看所有的东西
I would just take a look at pretty much all of it
因为那真的会帮助你们了解我们此刻在Hazel所构建的东西
because that's really going to help you out with what we're kind of building here at this moment in Hazel
我还会继续讲那个OpenGL系列，可能在下周，可能贯穿整个下周
and also I'm going to continue that OpenGL stories, probably next week, probably throughout this kind of next week
因为，再说一次，这对于深入研究这些概念非常重要
because it's, again, it's going to be really important in kind of taking a deeper look at some of these concepts
那是我们在游戏引擎系列中所学到的，无论如何，今天我们将讨论缓冲区布局
that we're learning here in the game engine series, so anyway, today we're going to talk about buffer layouts
所以那意味着什么，我们为什么需要它们，它们有什么作用，我们如何写它们
so what does that mean, why do we need them, what do they do, and how do we write them in a way
那既抽象又适用于每个渲染接口，而且实际上对我们来说也很容易使用
that is both abstract and works for every render api, but also is actually kind of easy for us to use
因为那就是我所关心的，对吧，我想要我们在客户端写的代码
because that's kind of what I'm all about, right, I want the code that we write on the client side
我们在游戏项目中写的代码，或者在渲染器中写的代码，都很漂亮
the code that we actually write like inside our game kind of project, right, or inside our renderer, it's just be beautiful
那就是我想要的，那就是我的目标，对吧，外面实际上天黑了
that's kind of what I go for, that's what I aim for, right, and it's actually getting dark outside
因为我今天把视频放得很晚，我只是在计划
because I left this video pretty late today, I was just planning it
确保我把我想说的都说明白了，因为我真的很喜欢，我真的很想做好这期
and just making sure that I had everything that I wanted to say figured out, because I really like, I really want to do this well
这特殊的一期，所有的都会跟着来，但你们知道这一期，所以如果天有点暗，我很抱歉
this specific episode, all videos really come on, but you know this specific episode, so if it kind of gets darker, I'm sorry
因为它听起来就像一组半，不管怎样，重点是漂亮的代码，对吧，我认为那很重要
because it is like the sounds about a set and half now, anyway, the point is beautiful code, right, I think that's really important
我认为如果你们写的代码，如果你们设计一个接口，写的代码，看起来很恶心
I think that if the code that you're writing, if you design an api, and the code that your writing, just looks disgusting
或者只是很难处理，或不够简洁，那就是个问题，对吧，想想写文档
or just is hard to do things with, or isn't concise enough, that's an issue, right, think about writing documentation
或者只是像英语SA那样写作，对吧，如果你们用一段又一段来描述同一个东西
or just writing like an English SA or something like that, right, if you take paragraphs and paragraphs to kind of describe the same thing
你们就不能写出漂亮的，流畅的句子，那听起来不太好，这对读者不好
and you just can't make really like nice, kind of flowing sentences, that doesn't really sound nice, it's not good for the reader reed
除此之外，并不是说它不好，除此之外，它实际上并不实用
and it, and just apart from that, not just like it's just not nice, aside from that, it's just not like actually practical
这种方法不太管用，因为这个人可能会把你们的句子读很多遍
it doesn't work as well, right like the person might have to read your sentence multiple times
或者他们可能不得不阅读更多的信息，否则他们必须理解
or they might have to read a whole much more information that they otherwise would have to understand
你们想用英语SA说什么，对吧，当然还有英语SA
what it is you're trying to say in your English SA, right and of course English SA
不管怎样，你们可能会有很高的工作量，所以可能会一遍又一遍地重复一些事情
you're probably going for a high work count, anyway, so you might just reiterate stuff over and over again
但事实并非如此，通常情况下你们会尽量简洁，对吧
but incur that's really not the case, usually like you actually are trying to be concise, right
一般来说，你们想要使用语法和句子，那在你们的SA中听起来都很不错
and just in general, you want to use kind of grammar and sentences, that both kind of sound nice kind of in your SA
对吧，在你们的英语SA中，回到这个，但也有些东西实际上可以非常简洁很好地表达观点
right, in your English SA, back to this, but also stuff that actually gets your point across very just concisely, and just nicely
这样人们就会想继续读下去，这样人们就会对你们想要做的事情形成一个良好的视觉形象
so that the person kind of wants to keep reading, and so that the person forms a good visual, kind of mental image of what it is you're trying to do
一切都很漂亮，一切都很扎实，那就是我们想要通过这个引擎中的所有接口实现的
and everything is just beautiful, and everything just feels solid, that's what we want to achieve with all of the apis in this engine
对吧，那就是我们想要做的，那并不容易做到，对吧，但因为使用的是像CPP，非常灵活
right, that is what we want to do, that's not easy to do, right, but because we're using a language like CPP, it's extremely flexible
这实际上意味着我们可以做很多我们想做的事情，特别是缓冲区布局
and it actually means that we can do a lot of what we're trying to do, and today specifically with buffer layout
我将向你们展示，做同样的事情可能有很多不同的方法
I'm going to show you how, there's probably there's many different ways of essentially doing the same thing
但我想用一种看起来不错的方式来做，就像我们在讨论缓冲区布局一样
but I want to do it in a way that actually looks good, like we're talking about a buffer layout
我们应该能够可视化代码，就像得到了一切，对吧，我得到了一切，就像不想要些奇怪的
we should just be able to visualize the code, and be like I get everything, right, I get everything, like we don't want some weird
就像用一种奇怪的方式来写这个缓冲区布局的代码，那是没有意义的
like weird kind of way of writing code for this buffer layout, where it just doesn't make sense
或者它只需要我们认真思考它是什么定义，不，我们希望它简单
or it just requires us to really think about what it is where defining, no, we want it just to be easy
希望它真的很简单，因为如果它很简单，如果很漂亮，对吧，优雅，那么除了看起来很好
we want it to just be really easy, because if it is easy, and if it is just so nice, right, and elegant, then apart from just looking good
我们对自己感觉很好，也是处理这些问题的人，这样很好，很容易
and us feeling good about ourselves, and also are the people dealing with this, and being like this is great, this is so easy
除此之外，它还能减少代码中的错误，为什么，因为一切都是有意义的
apart from that, it's also actually going to reduce the bugs in our code, why, because everything just makes sense
如果有什么问题，我们可以直观地发现，我们不需要只阅读文档，然后说
and if something is wrong, we can intuitively kind of just pick up on that, we don't need to just read the documentation, and be like
我想那是错的，不，我们可以看到错误就在那里，因为它是这样放置的，错误很明显
yeah, I guess that's wrong, no, we can just see the errors right there, because it's lay down in such a way, where errors are obvious
好了，那就是我们今天要讲的内容，我们要开始了，先看一看
okay, that's what we're gonna talk about today, we're gonna jump in, and we're gonna take a look
只是一个我们实际拥有的例子，以及我们想要创建的东西
just the practical example of what we actually have, as well as talk about what it is we're trying to create
我认为那是非常重要的，当你们谈论任何一种想设计的接口或任何一种复杂的概念时
and I think that that's really important, when you talk about any kind of api that you want to design or any kind of complex concept
这就是这个实际在做什么，对吧，特别是顶点缓冲布局，它非常简单，我们正在做的就是
it's what is this actually doing, right, and with vertex buffer layout specifically, it's very simple, you know, what we're doing is
我们实际上是在告诉OpenGL，这个字节数组的数据，里面有什么，如何分解，有多少元素
we're actually telling OpenGL, this byte array of data, what's in it, how is it broken down, you know, how many elements are there
有多少元素，你们知道，这是一个3分量的浮点数向量，对吧，或者只是3个独立的浮点数
how many like what are the elements, you know, is this a 3 component vector of floats, right, or there's just 3 separate floats
你们知道，这是一个四种颜色的组件，它只是，也许它只是一个无符号整数
you know, is this a four kind of component color housing specified, it's just just, maybe it's just an unsigned integer
或者它可能是四个浮点数之类的，对吧，可以是任何东西，就像如果只是个二进制数据
you know, or maybe it's four several floats or something like that, right, it could be just absolutely anything, like if it's just a binary blob of data
这是我们的顶点缓冲区实际接收并上传到GPU的东西
which is what our vertex buffer actually takes in and uploads into the GPU
我们需要一些方法来描述数据的布局，这意味着，前四个字节可能是浮点数
we need some way to actually describe the layout of that data, which again means, you know, the first four bytes might be a float
第二个可能是另一个浮点数，然后第三个可能是另一个浮点数，那就是一行中的三个浮点数
the second four bytes might be another float, and then the third four bytes might be another float, that's three floats in a row
那就是我们的三分量向量，它描述了顶点位置，那就是我们想要达到的
that's our three component vector that describes our vertex position stuff like that, that's what we're trying to achieve
让我们试着用种优雅的方式来做，直接看个例子，然后看看我们是怎么做的，好了
let's try and do it in an elegant way, let's jump in take a look at a practical example, and we'll see how we go, okay
那么上次我讲了这个三角形，今天我们要达到同样的目的，但要更优雅，更具体
so last time I had this triangle, today we're going to basically aim to achieve the same thing, but a lot more elegantly and specifically
为了好玩，我们可能还会插入一些其他顶点属性，看看它们是如何运行的
we're also going to maybe jam in some other vertex attributes for fun, just to kind of see how they work
也许我们会添加一个顶点颜色或者类似的东西，让我们关闭这个
maybe we'll just throw on a vertex color or something like that, let's just close this
所以目前我们实际上是在指定缓冲区布局，如果没有，我们就不会在屏幕上看到任何东西
so currently we are actually specifying a buffer layout, right, if we weren't, we wouldn't see anything on the screen
也就是这里，对吧，就是这两行代码，它说的是在顶点缓冲区内
and that's this right here, okay, these two lines of code, what this is saying is inside our vertex buffer
我们创建的这个，在下标0处，有三个浮点数，对吧，它们没有标准化
this one that we're creating, we have at index 0, three floats, right, they're not normalized
每个顶点之间的步幅就是这个大小，所以3个浮点数，12字节，偏移量是空的，对吧
the stride between each vertex is that size, so three floats, 12 bytes, and the offset of this particular element is nothing, right
我不想过多地讨论它的原理，因为有个关于它的OpenGL视频，正如我所说，太阳正在落山
now I don't really want to discuss how this works too much, because I do have an OpenGL video about it, and as I said, the sun is setting
我和我妻子还有其他事情要做，我不想在这里看两个小时，只是重复浪费你们的时间
and I have like other stuff to do with my wife, and I don't want to see it here for two hours, just reiterating wasting your time
我只是描述了我已经知道的所有东西，所以一定要看看那期视频，但我不知道，就像这个
I'm just describing everything that I already have already, so definitely check out that video, but I don't know, like that this is like
它可能很容易理解，所以如果你们不理解这一行代码
it might be quite simple to understand, so if you don't understand this particular line of code
一定要看看那期视频，因为我不打算在这期讲太多
make sure you check out that video, because I'm not going to really talk about it too much, I think in this episode
所以对于这一行代码，我想指出的是它的连接
so a few things that I actually want to point out with this particular line of code is, I guess the linkages of it
所以它指的是什么，它连接的是什么，它对应的是什么，对吧
so what it's referring to, what it's linked to, what it corresponds to, right
那么顶点属性实际上存储在顶点数组中，而不是顶点缓冲区中
so vertex attributes specifically are actually stored in the vertex array, not the vertex buffer
现在它们描述顶点缓冲区中的数据，但是顶点数组是一种父类型
now they describe data in a vertex buffer, however a vertex array is kind of the parent type, if you will
一个顶点数组可以包含多个缓冲区，我们实际上可以交叉我们的缓冲区
and a vertex array can contain multiple buffers, right, we can actually inter leave our buffers
你们知道，在这个顶点中，对吧，在这个顶点中，什么类型的顶点，对吧，我们可以添加
and have, you know, just in this one vertice like, right, in this one, what kind of vertices are, right, we could just add
你们知道，我们想要顶点颜色或者顶点法线什么的，我们实际上可以添加它，就像那样
you know, we want a vertex color or vertex normal or something, we can actually just add it, like just Bam like that
这样你们就知道了所有的东西，在这种情况下我们所拥有的每一个顶点都会包含
you know, and that way you know everything, every single vertex that we have is kind of going to contain in this case
也许是位置和法线，或者我们可以做的另一个是不把它交织在一起，这样就没有这些了
maybe both a a position and a normal, right, or the other thing we could do is kind of just not inter leave it, so not have any of this
然后在这里创建另一种数组，另一个浮点数组，它有顶点和法线
right, but then just make another kind of array here, right, another float array, which has had vertex normals
然后我们可以把它上传到一个单独的顶点缓冲区，我们可以为法线创建另一个顶点缓冲区
and then we can actually upload that into a separate vertex buffer, we can create another vertex buffer just for the normals
然后另一个是颜色，然后另一个是，你们明白了，对吧
and then another one for the colors, and then another one for, you get, you get the point, right
正因为如此，OpenGL并不关心你们怎么做，可以交叉所有数据，在上面有一个大顶点
so because of that, OpenGL doesn't really care how you do that, you can interlet all your data, and have one big fat vertex above
这差不多就是你们想要的，顺便说一下，99%的情况下
which is pretty much what you want, like 99 percent of the case by the way
或者你们可以把顶点缓冲区分成不同的实际顶点缓冲区，和不同的内存缓冲区
or you can split up your vertex buffers into separate kind of actual vertex buffers, and separate buffers of memory
然后分别上传，没关系，因为这是一样的，对吧
and then upload them individually, it doesn't matter, because this stays the same, right
只是在描述顶点数组的时候，你们碰巧在不同的顶点缓冲区中绑定
it's just you happen to bind in different vertex buffers at certain times, when you actually describe your vertex array
我们可能会在下一期讨论这个问题，因为下一期我们将讨论顶点数组
and we'll kind of maybe talk about that in the next episode, because next episode we're going to talk about vertex arrays
并将它们抽象到一个类中，这意味着这些东西，无论如何，我想让你们知道的是
and actually abstracting them out into a class, which means this kind of stuff, anyway, what I want you to know is that
这个特殊的绑定，我启用了一个VertexAttribArray并指定，看看我的缓冲区的布局
this particular binding this kind of, I'm enabling a VertexAttribArray and specify, and look at the layout of my buffer
它存储在一个顶点数组中，如果我绑定另一个顶点缓冲区，不需要重新定义这个
that is stored in a vertex array, if I bind another vertex buffer, or something like if I don't need to redefine this
我所需要做的就是把这些东西保存到顶点数组中，如果我想重调它进行渲染的话
all I need to do is this stuff gets saved into my vertex array, if I want to recall it for rendering
我只是再一次绑定顶点数组，就完成了，第二个信息是它直接绑定到着色器上
I just simply bind my vertex array again, and it's done, okay, the second piece of information is that this is directly tied to our shader
如果我们看一个着色器，就像在这指定的，看这个，layout location = 0 vec3 a_Position
right, if we look at a shader, like we've specified one here, look at this, layout location equals 0, vec3 a_Position, right
那就是这个数据，矢量的三个分量，对吧，三个浮点数，那就是矢量，对吧
that's this piece of data, three component of vector, right, three floats, that's what a vector is, right
未标准化，3*sizeof(float), 也就是12字节，同样是这个类型的sizeof
not normalized, 3 times the sizeof float, 12 bytes, again, the sizeof this type
Index 0, layout = 0，而不是location = 0，
index 0, layout equals 0, rather location equals 0,
对吧，那就是它的联系，如果我们突然想要一个法线
right, that is what that's tied in with, if we suddenly want to take in a normal
对吧，我们把它放到位置1，我们用这个颜色，因为它是一个不同的类型，vec4
right, we put that in location 1, let's just go with the color in this case, because it's a different type, a vec4
这将是我们的顶点颜色，对吧，我们要做的是复制这个，对吧，我们在下标1处有它
and this will be our kind of vertex color, right, what we do, we do duplicate this, right, we have it at index 1
顺便说一下，我们还需要启用它，启用索引1，我们有四个浮点数
and by the way, we also need to enable it, so enabling index 1, we have four floats
然后剩下的是一样的，除了这个变化，因为它是开着的，顺便说一下，这是错误的
and then the press is kind of the same, except this changes, because that is on, this is wrong by the way
抱歉，这不是sizeof，这是stride，所以它实际上是每个顶点的sizeof，而不是元素的sizeof
sorry, this isn't the sizeof, I should, this is the stride, so it's actually the sizeof each vertex, not the sizeof each element, right
它是数组中每个顶点之间的大小，如果我们有三个顶点，它是每个完整顶点的大小
so it's kind of the size between each vertex in the array, so if we have three vertices, it's the sizeof each full vertex
在这个例子中，是位置和颜色的sizeof，也就是7*sizeof(float)
which would be the sizeof both the position and the color in this case, which would actually be 7 times sizeof float
那对它们来说是一样的，所以这个变成了这个，对吧
and that would be the same for both of them, so this changes to this, right
然后偏移量是，这个特定元素的偏移量，对吧，在缓冲区内，所以很明显这是vec3
and then the offset is, the offset of this particular element, right, inside the buffer, so obviously this is vec3
那是12个字节，3个浮点数，对吧，就是12个字节
that's 12 bytes, 3 floats, right, 12 bytes
所以这个的偏移量是12，所以它就是12，对吧
so the offset of this is going to be 12, so it's simply 12, right
我们只需要将它强制转换为一个const void*，好了，所以那就是我们最终得到的
and we just need to cast it to a const void pointer, okay, const, okay, so that's kind of what we end up with
但你们可以看到它直接绑定到我的着色器上，那就是我想在这里强调的一点
but you can see that is directly tied to my shader, that's the kind of the point that I want to drive home right here is
它被绑定到我的着色器上，在OpenGL中它并不是绑定在两个着色器上
it's tied to my shader, okay, and it's actually not really tied 2 shaders in OpenGL
在这种意义上，在这之间没有执行验证，在DirectX中，它是绝对执行的
in the sense that there's no validation performed between that, in DirectX, it is absolutely performed
对吧，你们不能描述一个顶点缓冲区，直到绑定了一个着色器
right, you can not describe a vertex buffer until you've bound a shader
好了，所以这实际上和OpenGL的原理有点不同
okay, so it's actually a bit different than how OpenGL works
不管怎样，那就是我的观点，因为它与我的着色器紧密相连
anyway, that's kind of my point, so because it's so heavily tied with my shader
我实际上想为我的缓冲布局做的是
what I actually want to kind of do for my buffer layout is
我只是想在顶点缓冲区上设置一个缓冲区布局，现在我看到了，它们被绑定到顶点数组上
I basically just want to be able to set a buffer layout onto a vertex buffer, right, now I did just see that, they're tied to vertex arrays
然而，布局描述，就像布局是特定于顶点缓冲区一样，它描述了实际内存缓冲区的布局
however a layout describes, like a layout is specific to a vertex buffer, it describes a layout of an actual buffer of memory
OpenGL在顶点数组中存储状态，在DirectX中，在顶点缓冲区中
so whilst OpenGL kind of stores the state in vertex array, in DirectX, that specifically on vertex buffer is
因为在DirectX中没有顶点数组这种东西，但除此之外，它对我们来说更有意义
because there's no such thing as a vertex array in DirectX, but apart from that, it just makes, it just makes more sense to us
所以对我们来说，它们是否存储在顶点数组中并不重要，因为我们仍然可以解决这个问题
so to us, it doesn't really matter that they're actually stored inside vertex arrays, because we can still kind of work around that
把它们存储在我们喜欢的任何地方，它只是在最后，在背后，当我们需要的时候，会做区分
and store them wherever we like, it is just in the end, under the hood, we'll make that differentiation, when we need to
但是表面接口仍然应该将它设置到顶点缓冲区，现在我如何描述这个布局
but the surface level api should still set it onto the vertex buffer, now how do I describe this layout
这儿有很多种实现方法，但我不想浪费你们的时间，只给你们看不好的解题方法
well there's a lot of ways that you could do it, but I'm not going to waste your time, and show you all the bad ways of doing it
我会给你们展示一种很好的方法，也就是我所说的，我们想要有一种优雅的视觉表示
I'll just show you a nice way of doing it, which is again what I'm talking about, where we want to kind of have an elegant visual representation of this
这不是很酷吗，如果我们描述这个布局
wouldn't it be cool, if when we describe this layout
我们可以有这样的代码，就像这里，你们知道的，我们的布局等于
we could somehow literally just have this kind of code, like right here, and just be like you know our layout equals
也许把这个放在括号里，我们的布局等于这样，现在让我，我刚刚意识到
kind of maybe put this in brackets, our layout equals like that, right, now let me just, I just realized
我有一些我们不需要的空格，如果我们可以那样做，不是很好吗
I've got white spaces on which we don't need, wouldn't it be nice, if we could just do something like that
那就是我们要做的，我们实际上要创建它，这样我们就能看到布局的视觉表现
well that's kind of what we're gonna do, we're gonna actually literally make it, so that we can see a visual representation of our layout
所以我们的目标是有一个叫做BufferLayout类的东西，它看起来像这样
so our goal is to have something that's maybe called a BufferLayout class, right, which is going to look like this
然后我们可能会得到每个元素都是这样定义的
and then maybe what we'll have is each element is going to be kind of defined like this
好了，我们将通过使用一个初始化的列表来实现这个
okay, and we're going to achieve this by just using an initialized list
可能把这些元素存储在一个向量中，现在我们不打算使用vec3或vec4，这里有一个GLM类型
and probably storing these elements in a vector, now we're not going to use it vec3 or vec4, there's a glm types in this case
这里它们显然是OpenGL着色器语言中的glsl类型
well and here they are obviously the glsl types inside the OpenGL shading language
但我们实际要做的是，创建一些枚举，来描述这个数据类型
but what we're actually gonna do is, come up with some kind of enum, that describes this data type
所以我们本质上可能会创建一个枚举类ShaderDataType
so we're essentially gonna probably create like an enum class called like ShaderDataType
这就是我们的跨接口跨平台，我们只是在shader中定义每种数据类型
which will be kind of our cross api cross platform we're just kind of defining each data type that is inside a shader
那么比如vec3 vec4，你们知道float, int之类的，所以可能会用Float3来描述一个三分量
so like vec3 vec4, you know float, int that kind of stuff, so we'll probably use something called like Float3 to describe a three component thing
你们知道的，vec3很酷，但我有点喜欢Float3，那就是HLSL的风格
you know vec3 is cool, and all but I kind of like Float3, that's kind of the HLSL style way of doing things
我们可能最终会切换到HLSL着色器，如果你们愿意的话，也可以使用vec3
and we are probably going to eventually switch to HLSL shaders, you can use vec3, if you want
因为那有点像我们的数学库，但我要用Float3来描述一个3分量的浮点数
because that's kind of tied to our math library in like at the moment, but I'm just going to use Float3 to describe a 3 component float
对吧，因为这是有意义的，然后可能会给它一个名字，现在你们真的不需要给它一个名字
right, because it makes sense, and then we'll probably give it a name, now you don't really need to give it a name
给它一个名字很有用，比如在DirectX中，我们需要提供某种字符串，你们以后会发现，但是
it's useful to give it a name, like in DirectX, we will have to supply some kind of string, as you'll find out in the future, but
给它起个名字很好，这样你们就知道这实际上是什么了
it's just nice to kind of give it a name, just so that you know what this actually is
如果你们想的话，可以把它叫做一样的东西，在这个例子中我就是这么做的，所以可能会有
and if you want you can actually call it the same thing, which is what I'm kind of doing in this case, so we might have that
我们还是把颜色去掉吧，我的意思是，你们知道的，对颜色做同样的处理
let's just get rid of this whole color thing, I mean essentially you do the same thing for color though
你们只需要创建vec，比如Float4，做所有这些，看起来会很漂亮，对吧，要去掉颜色
you just make a vec, like a Float4 and do all of that, and that's gonna look really nice, right, we'll get rid of color here
我们会去掉这些东西，变回三个浮点数，我们会试着先渲染那个三角形
and we'll get rid of this stuff, changes back to three floats, and we'll try and just render that triangle to begin with
好了，所以这是我的布局，然后我要设置布局，那就是我想要找到布局的方式
okay, so this is my layout, and then I'll set my layout, and that's kind of it, that's actually how I wanted to find my layout
你们可以看到它变得非常漂亮，因为突然间我有了一个布局，里面充满了我需要的东西
and you can see that it becomes really nice, because suddenly if I have a layout, that's full of like stuff that I need
你们知道的，我们可能有纹理坐标之类的东西
you know, like you know, we might have like texture coordinates or something
你们知道的，有一些像贴图坐标和法线，然后还可能有颜色之类的
and you know, you have something like tex coord and maybe normals, and then you might have like a color or anything
很容易看到这个缓冲区的布局，对吧，太棒了，那就是我所要做的
it's just so easy to see the layout of this buffer, right, it's amazing, that's all I need to do
显然，如果我想要一个数组，比如，如果我想让它标准化，我可以添加第三个参数
and obviously if I want to like have an array of things, like you know, if I want it to be normalized or not, I can maybe add third parameter
但这就是我们想要的，所以让我们来看看实现这一切的魔法
but this is kind of what we're going for, so let's take a look at the magic to make this happen
所以我将在Buffer.h文件中定义所有这些代码，因为它与缓冲区布局和所有这些东西有关
so I'm going to define all this code inside the buffer file here, because it is to do with buffer layouts and all that stuff
所以我要创建BufferLayout类，一个BufferLayout本质上包含一个BufferElements的向量
so I'm going to make a class called BufferLayout, okay, and a BufferLayout is essentially going to contain a vector of BufferElements
好了，这些将被称为m_Elements，我马上给它一个getter来返回那个
okay, and these are going to be called m_Elements, I'm immediately just going to give it a getter to return that
因为我们需要它，所以就是GetElements() const，它会返回m_Elements，好了
because we are gonna need that, so GetElements const, and that will return m_Elements, okay
然后这些缓冲元素将是另一个类，实际上我将把它抽象成struct BufferElement
and then these buffer elements are going to be another class, actually I'll pull this a struct BufferElement
这将包含所有我们需要指定的东西，好了，第一个属性，它将包含一个名字
and this is going to contain all of the stuff that we need to actually specify, okay, so the first thing, it will contain is a name
那么就是std::string Name，我的意思是没有特定顺序，需要Offset和Size，还需要什么
so std::string Name, I mean in no particular order, we need the Offset, we need the Size, we need, what else do we need
我猜是Count，因为我们可以有很多这样的东西，老实说，我不确定我们是否需要它
the Count, I guess, because we can have like multiple of these, I'm not really sure if we need that, to be honest
因为我只是在想，我们肯定需要统一变量，如果我们有一个数组，但我们通常不需要
because I'm just thinking about it, like we definitely need that for uniforms, if we have like an array, but we don't generally
我想如果我们只有那个ShaderDataType，它将是数据的类型
I think if we just have that ShaderDataType as I said, which is going to be the Type of data
我们大概知道我们有多少个元素，不管怎么样
we'll kind of know the count of how many elements we have, anyway
我们总是可以创建辅助函数来在两者之间进行转换，对吧
and we can always create helper functions to kind of convert between the two, right
所以我们可能有Name，Type，Size，然后是Offset，我认为那应该足够了，对吧
so we maybe have the Name, the Type, the Size, and then the Offset, and I think that should be enough, right
现在我们在这里构造这个的方法是先写类型，对吧，然后是实际的名称
now the way that we constructed this over here was just by writing the type first, right, and then the actual name
所以我们在这里也可以这样做，我们只需要创建一个构造函数来允许那种构造，对吧
so we can actually do that here as well, we just need to create a constructor that allows that kind of construction, right
所以我写const std::string& name，然后是ShaderDataType type，对吧
so I'll write const std::string& name, and then ShaderDataType type, all right
然后在这里，我们将设置所有内容，因此Name将设置为name, Type是type, Size是0
and then over here, we will set everything, so Name will set to name, the Type will set to type, Size will set to 0
老实说，Size，我们可以立即计算，我认为，因为那只是Type的sizeof
to be honest, Size, we can calculate pretty much immediately, I think, because that's just the sizeof the Type
所以我们可能不需要设置它，尽管我们可以在这里设置一个默认值，然后我们将Offset设为0
so we probably don't need to set that although, we can here as a default, and then Offset, we'll set a 0 Offset
只有有了context，我们才能计算，Offset是这个元素在布局中的偏移量
we can really only calculate, once we have context, so Offset is going to be the offset of this element inside our layout
显然，要计算Offset，我们需要知道所有的元素，因为如果这是第二个元素
so obviously to calculate the Offset, we need to be aware of all the elements in there, because if this is like the second element
它的Offset将是第一个元素的sizeof，对吧，因为这是它进入缓冲区的大小
its Offset is going to be the sizeof the first element, right, because that's how much into the buffer it is
所以我们不能在这里计算，但是我们可以计算它的大小，所以可以那样做
so we can't really calculate that just here, but we can calculate the size, so we might do that
总之，enum class ShaderDataType，我们可以这样做
anyway, enum class ShaderDataType, right, and we can make this like
我的意思是，如果你们想，可以让这个像uint8_t或只是很小的东西，因为它真的不需要很大
I mean, if you wanted to, you can make this like uint8_t or something just tiny, because it doesn't really need to be very big
从字面上说，这并不重要，你们知道的，我不是那种认为这不会序列化，这不是
literally, it doesn't really matter, you know, I'm not one to just like this isn't gonna be serialized, this is not like
也许当我们尝试着完整地打包这些数据时，我们可以在以后来做那个
maybe if it comes down to us trying to really pack this data entirely, we can do that in the future
但你们暂时不需要，我们有None，Float，Float2
but you don't need to in the, like the time being, so we'll have None, we'll have Float, we'll have Float2
我们会有Float3，我们会有Float4，我们会有，我想我们还会有Mat3 Mat4
we'll have Float3, we'll have Float4, we'll have, I guess we'll can do like Mat3 Mat4
这不仅仅是描述属性，顺便说一下，它可以描述所有东西，我们有Int，Int2, Int3, Int4
this is not just gonna describe attributes, by the way, it can describe everything, we'll have Int, we'll have Int2 Int3 Int4
嗯，是的，那可能已经足够好了，我们可能有Struct或像统一变量之类，我们到了那里就会过
um yeah that's probably good enough, we might have Struct or something for like Uniforms, we'll cross that bridge when we get there
好了，对我来说，看起来很好，这是个很好的基本类型，也可以有布尔，也许这里只写Bool
okay, that looks pretty good to me, it is a good like basic type, you can have Boolean as well, maybe I'll just write Bool at the end here
好了，那很好，对吧，那描述了所有关于类型的内容，现在我关心的两件事是Size和Offset
okay, that's pretty pretty good, right, so that describes all about types, now two things I'm concerned about is a Size and also the the Offset
我们可以拿上计算出来，所以我们能做的就是创建某种函数
which we can calculate in a minute, so what we can do is create some kind of function
显然，这种ShaderDataType和实际大小之间的转换
obviously the converts between this kind of ShaderDataType and an actual size
所以我们可以做的就是创建一个静态的uint32_t ShaderData，只实现ShaderDataTypeSize
so what we can do is just create a static uint32_t ShaderData, you know, we can just do ShaderDataTypeSize I guess
ShaderDataTypeSize(ShaderDataType type)，然后这会简化我括号中的字母
ShaderDataTypeSize(ShaderDataType type), and then this will simply my letter e seens at the jam
因为我不能在不用力的情况下输入它，这将是一个switch语句
because I can't type it without pressing hard, this is just gonna be a switch to seem, this is just gonna be a switch statement
它基本上是在，是在我们有的类型上switch，所以就是ShaderDataType
the go is between the basically, just switches on every single type that we have, so ShaderDataType
你们知道的，给它赋值Float，在这种情况下，它有点，然后我有，让我们现在是1,2,3,4
you know, give it Float, and in this case, you know, it just kind of, and then I have, let's just go one two three four for now
这只是返回sizeof，浮点数是4个字节，所以它会返回那么多
this just returns the sizeof it, so a float is four bytes, so it's gonna return that much
我们也会对其他的类型做同样的处理，Float2, Float3, Float4, Mat3, Mat4，试着更全面些
and we'll also kind of do the same for pretty much everything else, so a Float2 Float3 Float4, Mat3 Mat4, I'm gonna try and be comprehensive
通常我喜欢加入这些东西，因为这只需要一点
usually I like adding these things as like go, just because this just takes needle
这会花很多时间，让视频变得更复杂，但至少现在我要这么做
this just takes a bunch of time, and makes the video more complicated, but I'll do it at least for this for now
因为它不会花太多时间，好吧，我想就那样了，所有这些，对吧，我可以把它们对齐一点
because it shouldn't take too much time, all right, I think that's it, so all of these, right, I can just align these a bit, okay
所以Float2将是4*2，Float3将是3*4，Mat3将是3*3，因为是3×3矩阵
so Float2 is gonna be 4 times 2, Float3 is gonna be times 3 times 4, right, a Mat3 is gonna be times 3 times 3, right, because the 3 by 3 matrix
Float4和4×4矩阵是一样的，它会是4，它会是，它会是，它会是2
a Float4 is gonna be the same about 4 by 4 matrix, and it's gonna be 4, you know, and it's gonna be, and it two's gonna be that
你们可以理解这一点，然后是Bool类型，我不确定，我之前可能是1，我们会看到的
that that you guys can get the point, and then a Bool probably, I'm not sure, I might be one by my before, we'll see about that
我们现在就把它设为1，如果我们什么都没有，显然是返回0，我们还应该在这里断言
we'll just leave it as one for now, and obviously one of 10 0, if we have nothing, and also we should definitely assert here
HZ_CORE_ASSERT(false， "Unknown ShaderDataType")，不需要打印类型，因为在这中断
HZ_CORE_ASSERT(false, "Unknown ShaderDataType"), okay, and we don't need to print out the type, because that will just break here
我们可以自己用调试器检查它，好了，一切都好了，希望我没有出错
and we can just inspect it using the debugger ourselves, okay, there we go, that's everything, hopefully I didn't make any mistakes
我在这有点匆忙，但现在可以看到，每个数据的类型是什么，对吧，记住，现在是在缓冲区
I was kind of hasteful here, but now we can actually see, what the type of each piece of data is, right, now this is in buffer, remember
当我们把这个移到着色器中并有更多的东西时，我们会处理这个，好了，很酷，对吧
when we actually move this into shaders and have more stuff, we'll deal with that kind of, then okay, cool, right
所以我们现在要做的是计算这个大小，对吧，这里是大小
so what we want to do now is actually calculate that size, right, so right here in size
我们已经可以调用ShaderDataTypeSize()，然后传递type，好了，然后我们就有了，漂亮
we can already just call ShaderDataTypeSize(), and then passing the type, alright, and then we have that, beautiful
这只是BufferElement，当然不是，当我们创建BufferLayout时，对吧
now and this is just BufferElement, of course not BufferElements, when we create a BufferLayout, right
我们想要做的是接收并初始化一个列表之类的
what we want to be able to do is take in and initialize a list, right, so this kind of thing
这很有趣，因为最终，你们可以看到，我只是想取一个常数向量，对吧
now this this is interesting, because ultimately, you could just see, I just want to take in like a constant vector, right
因为如果你们取一个向量，没什么关系，如果它是常量引用之类的，那就不那么烦人了
because if you take in a vector, and it doesn't matter, if it's constant reference or whatever, that let it ease annoying me
这无关紧要，如果它是const引用或其他什么，但如果你们把它传进来，就像这样应该有用
it doesn't matter, if it's const reference or whatever, but if you take that in, like this kind of should work
它没有，因为这里发生了2个隐式转换，但是你们看，如果我们取这个类型
it doesn't, because there's 2 implicit casts happening, but just see that you know, you know, if we just take this type
从技术上讲，我们改变了它，使它成为这种类型，对吧，那实际上是可行的，对吧
technically speaking, and we change that, and make it this type, right, that will actually work, right
所以你们实际上可以构造这样的东西，现在它不运行了，这个，我们把它放错了方向
so you can actually construct something like this, now it's not working, this, yeah we've kind of put this the wrong way around
我不知道我是怎么做到的，也很简单，所以把类型放在前面，然后是实际列表中的名字
I don't know how I did that, so easily as well, so we put the type first, and then the name in our actual list here
如果我们去掉这个，然后返回，它应该可以运行，好了
so if we get rid of this, and get back, it should work, yeah there we go
然后你们能做的就是决定我要做一个布局，从我的布局中布局
see and then what you can do is actually decide that I want to make a layout, layout from my layout, right
我不能把这个布局画出来，但不管怎样，你们懂的，但不幸的是，我不能这么做，好了
can't really pull this layout, but whatever, you get the point, right, but unfortunately, I can't just do this, okay
因为有一个隐式强制转换可以将一个向量，比如一个初始化的列表转换为一个向量
because there's one implicit cast to convert a vector, like an initialized list into a vector
和另一个隐式强制转换，将vector转换为BufferLayout，因为BufferLayout有一个构造函数
and another implicit cast to convert the vector into a BufferLayout, because BufferLayout has a constructor
那需要一个向量，所以我们不能那样做，我们能做的是在这里输入一个初始化列表，对吧
that takes in vector, so we can't actually do that, what we can do however is actually just take in an initializer list here, right
然后如果我们真的那样做了，对吧，那么你们知道，就可以在这里做const引用
and then if we actually do that, right, then you know, you can do like your const reference here
如果我们这样做，你们可以看到效果很好，好了，漂亮，现在基本上得到了想要的，酷
if we do that, you can see this works, okay, beautiful, so now we basically got exactly what we wanted, which is pretty cool
然后从这个，对吧，我们如何转化成一个向量，就像我说的，这显然是一个有构向量
and then from this, right, how do we convert into a vector, well as I said, there's obviously a constructive vector
它接受一个初始化的列表，所以我们就这样做
that takes in an initialized list, so we literally just do
我想我会这样做，可能是layout或elements，就像那样
I guess I'll do, maybe layout or elements, will call it, just like that
好了，现在我们可以从这里构造一个这样的向量，所有我们说过的数据都在这个向量里
okay, there we go, so now we can construct one of these from here, and all of the data that we've actually said is inside this vector
这很酷，一旦我们有了这个向量，我们实际上需要计算偏移量，我写计算偏移量
which is very cool, now once we have that vector, we actually need to calculate the offsets, so I'll say calculate offsets
我们还需要一个信息，那就是步幅，步幅就是每个顶点的大小
and there's one more piece of information that we need, and that is the stride, and the stride is the size of each vertex
它是完整顶点，所以所有的属性，所有这些的大小，只有在我们有了整个列表之后才知道
it's complete vertex, so all of the attributes, the size of all of those together, that's only known after we had the whole list
和偏移量一样，我们可以计算它，一旦有了整个列表，不能在BufferLayoutElement中这样做
same as the offset, right, so we can calculate that, once we have the whole list, we can't do that inside BufferLayoutElement
但我们可以在这里做那个，所以我们创建uint32_t m_Stride，默认设置为0
but we can do that here, so we'll make a uint32_t called m_Stride, will set a 0 by default
CalculateOffsetsAndStride将是我们这里的一个漂亮函数，它将是private
CalculateOffsetsAndStride will be a beautiful function that we have here, that's gonna be private, private
那么就是void CalculateOffsetsAndStride，它会遍历所有列表，我们这里的所有元素
so void CalculateOffsetsAndStride, that's going to go through all of the list, all the elements that we have here
所以我想我们会看到，就是for (auto& element : m_Elements)，对吧
so I guess we'll just see, for auto reference elements in this letter is really annoying me, in elements, right
我们要做的是在这里保持偏移量，然后我想我们可以在这里设置m_Stride = 0
and what we're gonna do is we're gonna maintain an offset here, and then I guess we can set m_Stride equal to 0 here
以防我们重新计算什么的，这就是我们要做的，会看到element.Offset=offset
just in case we recalculated or something, this is what we're gonna do, we're just gonna see that the element.Offset, right, is gonna be our offset
然后我们看到offset += element.Size，对吧，然后我们还会看到m_Stride += element.Size
then we're going to see offset += element.Size, right, and then we're also going to see, m_Stride += element.Size
好了，所以那个应该会设置所有的偏移量，也会计算整个BufferLayout的stride
okay, so that should set all the offsets, and all the, and also calculate the stride for our entire BufferLayout
嗯，我想就那么了，说实话，我们还没有做什么，我想所有的事情，我不知道
um that's, I think that's about it, to be honest, what what haven't we done, I think everything's, well I don't know
我们应该检查下，看看是否有效，还没有m_VertexBuffer->SetLayout()，马上就会做那个
we should just check it out, and see if it works, so um we haven't done m_VertexBuffer->SetLayout(), we'll do that in a second
我在这里放一个断点，启动这个，看看这个布局是不是我们想要的样子
I'll just gonna put a break point here, launch this, and see if that layout is everything that we wanted to be
更潜在的是，我可能应该添加些其他的来做布局，因为你们知道，我的意思是，这会很无聊
and more potentially, I should probably add something else that did a layout, because just you know, I mean, this is gonna be pretty boring
如果我们只有一个元素，但如果我们看一下，我们的布局只有一个元素，那是对的，就是12
I think if we just have one thing in there, but if we take a look, so our layout has one element, that's right of 12, which is correct
这个位置的偏移量为0，大小为12，好了，看起来不错，让我们再测试一下，再添加两个
and the position has an offset of 0 size of 12, okay, looks good, let's just to test it a bit more, I'm gonna add 2 more things
我要添加另一个Float3，然后是一个Float4，也许我要把Float4放在中间，只是让它有点不同
I'm going to add a another Float3 and then a Float4, maybe I'll put the Float4 in the middle, just to make it a bit different
所以我们假装有正常的颜色，我们会看到它是什么样子的，好了，我要看到的，没有编译
so we'll pretend that, we have normal in the color, we'll see what that looks like, okay, that I was gonna see, I didn't compile
但那是因为把逗号放在了错误的地方，让我们在这里再试下，layout，这个Stride是40，对吗
but that's because we put the comma in the wrong place, let's just try again here, okay, so layout, this Stride is 40, is that correct
16+4+12，是正确的，24+16，大小为3
so 16+4+12 yep, that's correct, 24+16, sizes 3
这些应该有正确的偏移量，偏移量为12，偏移量为28
and these should have correct offsets, offset of 12 and offset of 28
很漂亮，好了，那么继续，布局很好，那很酷，那么现在让我们尝试用它来渲染一些东西
beautiful, okay, so there we go, layout clearly works, and that is really cool, so now let's try and render something with it
我要做的是进入Buffer类，对吧，到Buffer.h文件
what I want to do is go into our Buffer class, right, to our Buffer.h file
然后添加virtual void SetLayout() BufferLayout，把它作为常量引用 layout，等于0
and just add you know a virtual void SetLayout(), right, BufferLayout, take that in as a constant reference layout, equals 0
然后还会有virtual const BufferLayout& GetLayout()，所以希望能够获取和设置布局，对吧
and then we'll also have a virtual const BufferLayout& GetLayout(), so I want to be able to get and set the layout, right
我们会打开OpenGLVertexBuffer，或者GLBuffer
we'll open up OpenGLVertexBuffer, or rather GLBuffer
在这里，这些都应该被覆盖，顺便说一下，不知道为什么它们没有
and inside here, these should all be overrides by the way, not sure why they're not
因为我太懒了，现在我们会有const override，这两个，GetLayout
because I was lazy I guess, so now we're gonna have constant override for all of this, and these two, well GetLayout
在这个作用域布局中，我们会有BufferLayout m_Layout, GetLayout会返回它
so into a scope layout here, so we'll have BufferLayout m_Layout, m_Layout, GetLayout is just going to return it
感谢VS提供了这么？的格式，然后这个会设置它，对吧，所以就是m_Layout = layout
and thank you visual studio for that horrendous formatting, and then this is just going to set it, right, so m_Layout equals layout
我要把这两个都做成，那还不错，好了，搞定，那么继续
I'll make both these, yeah that's fine, okay, done, so there we go
我要把它们做成内联的，但是没有意义了，已经是了
I was gonna make them inline, but there's no point, that is done
现在应该可以用这个来摇摆了，正如我提到的，这个特殊的代码是被设置在顶点数组中
now we should be able to just rock and roll with this, now as I mentioned, this particular code is get, it gets set in the vertex array
我们将在下期视频中讨论，因为我们还没有抽象出来，所以现在我们只在这里做这些
we'll talk about that next video, because we haven't abstracted that just yet, so for now we'll just do that stuff here
你们就会看到它是如何运行的，但在下一期，我们会把它移到合适的位置
and you'll kind of see how it works, but in the next episode, we'll move it into the appropriate location
我可以在这里结束这一期，但我不打算这样做，因为我真的想看，这些东西的运行和渲染
I could there end the episode here, but I'm not going to, just because I actually want to see, this stuff in action and rendering
我向你们保证过顶点颜色，为了让这个东西运行，我需要做的是遍历布局中的每个元素
and I did promise you guys vertex colors, okay, so to make this stuff work, what I need to do is iterate through every element in the layout
现在我可以写些代码，比如const auto& element inside layout.GetElements，但不想这样做
now I could write codes such as you know, for const auto& element inside layout.GetElements, but I don't want to
我只是想写这样的代码，这样看起来更好，那么在BufferLayout中
I just wanna write code like this, because it just looks better, so in BufferLayout
我要做的就是和我们在Layer中做的一样的事情
what I'm gonna do to make that happen is the same thing that we did inside a Layer
如果你们还记得，不好意思，在LayerStack中，我们实际上提供了迭代器begin和end
if you remember which is where I actually, sorry inside LayerStack, we're actually provided iterators begin and end
所以如果复制这段代码，然后进入Buffer
so if we copy this code, and then go into Buffer
在BufferLayout GetElements()中，我可以在这里提供个迭代
inside BufferLayout GetElements(), I can just provide an iterated here
显然在这个例子中，它将是一个BufferElement而不是一个Layer
obviously in this case, it's going to be a BufferElement instead of a Layer
然后这将是m_Elements begin和end
and then this is just going to be m_Elements begin and end
好了，现在我们可以这样做了，看起来很不错，我们需要遍历布局中的每个元素
and there we go, okay, so now we can just do that, which just looks nice, so we either I need through every element in the layout
我们只是想在这里做这样的事情，所以我们会跟踪我们要用到的下标
and we just want to do this kind of stuff here, so we'll keep track of which index we're up to
对吧，可以只用一个常规的for循环，这是内置的，但这也可以，这里的上标是什么
right, could have just used a regular for loops, that has built in, but this is also fine, what's up the index here
然后我们增加索引，这就是有趣的地方，好了，所以OpenGL需要的是
and then we'll increment the index, now this is where it gets interesting, okay, so what we need for OpenGL is
我们不能只看到它，它是vec3，我们必须看到它实际上是3个浮点数
we can't just see that, it's a vec3, we have to see that it's actually 3 floats
我们必须设置类型，然后是计数，就好像它不是一个变量，现在交互式，你们不需要做那个
we have to set the type, and then the count, as if it's like not one variable, now interactives, you don't, you don't do that
你们看，这是一个四分量向量，或者这是一个三分量向量，或者一个二分量向量
you just see, you know, this is a four component vector, or this is a three component vector, or a two component vector
所以那就是为什么，就像我没有，这就是为什么我没有把它写出来，就像，你们知道的
so that's why, like I don't, that's why I haven't written this in a way, that is just like, you know
type和count，就像我们让type为float，然后count为3，那很奇怪，我不喜欢那样做
type and count, as if we have type being float, and then count being 3, that's weird, I don't like doing it that way
无论如何，DirectX不是其中之一，所以我们在这里需要进行某种转换
and DirectX isn't one of that way, anyway, so what we need here is some kind of conversion to take place
这就很好了，不管怎样，元素都有分量计数，因为这样就可以了
so will be nice, if just regardless, elements just had a component count, right, because that will just make that work
所以让我们回到Buffer，把它加进去，BufferElement，会产生一点
so let's go back into Buffer, and actually just add that in, so BufferElement, will make a little
可能是这里的某种GetComponentCount的东西，我们可能会
um probably some kind of GetComponentCount thing here, right mmm, we can probably like
我不确定最好的方法是什么，我猜，我不认为，天气会经常冷到我们可以缓存它
I'm not sure what the best way to do this would be, I guess, I don't think, it's gonna be cold often enough for us to cache that
rule在内存中，那会很烦人，也许我们可以看到GetElementCount
and rule in the kind of just so that in memory, that'll be annoying, so maybe we can just see GetElementCount
然后我们可以在这里做一些转换，想想这个，如果我们在这里设置const，可能没问题
and then we can maybe just do some kind of switch here, just thinking about this, yeah it's probably fine, if we just make const here
然后我们会在这里switch类型，如果有个ShaderDataType::Float3，就会返回3，好了
and then we'll switch on the type here, and we'll see that, if we have a ShaderDataType::Float3, we'll just return 3, okay
那是一个组件，我们在这里返回0，并断言我们有一个未知类型
and that is the component cap what we'll return 0 here, and assert saying that we have an unknown type
再说一次，这种情况不应该发生，但可能会发生，我想，因为我是个好人
again this shouldn't really happen ever, but it might, and I guess, because I'm a good person
尽管我说过可能不会，会摸索出剩下的，我们从Float开始，然后有Float2 Float3 Float4
even though I said I probably wouldn't, will feel out the rest of these, so we'll start with Float, then we'll have Float2, Float3,Float4
然后是Int，哦，Int2 Int3 Int4，还有Mat4之类的，当然，我们可能不需要Mat4和Mat3
then Int, oops, Int2 Int3 Int4, what else we have Mat Mat4 and stuff, okay, sure, ah, we probably don't need Mat4 and Mat3
跟你们说实话，因为这其中之一会很好
to be completely honest with you, because it's one of these gonna be well
我不知道，这是那里的组件计数，它不仅仅用于属性，所以我们可能需要它
and I don't know, this is the component count of there, it's not gonna be used just for attributes, so we might need that
然后在这里，我想我们会有一个bool类型，这显然是1，这是4，这是3，这是2
and then over over here, I guess we'll have a bool, so that's obviously 1, that's 4, that's 3, that's 2
那是1，Mat4将是4*4，Mat3将是3*3，Float4将是4 2 1，对我来说这看起来很好
that's 1, Mat4 is going to be 4*4, Mat3 is gonna be 3*3, Float4 is gonna be 4, 2,1, alright, that looks pretty good to me
让我们把它TAB过来，让我们试着把它对齐，这样看起来更好看
let's just tab this across, and let's kind of try and align this somewhat, just so that it looks nice
继续，好了，酷，那么继续，现在我们得到了元素计数
and there we go, okay, cool, so there we go, now we've got the element count
抱歉，不是ElementCount，这是GetComponentCount，好了，所以这就是这里有多少个组件
sorry, not ElementCount, this is GetComponentCount, okay, so this is just how many components essentially we have here
现在不幸的是，我们还需要，我们有了分量容量
now unfortunately we also need, so we've got the component cap
但我们还需要实际的OpenGL类型，这就像base类型，我们不能有vec3，需要特别的float
but we also need the actual OpenGL type, and this is like the base type, we can't have like vec3, we need specifically float
所以我们还需要一些东西来解决这个，现在不太喜欢我们实际拥有的类型，显然是在元素中
so we also need something that figures that out, now I don't really like the type that we actually have, obviously is inside our element
它就像我们的，就像我们的element.Type
and it is like our, like you know, we have like element.Type essentially
那是我们的ShaderDataType，我要做的是在这里写一个函数，它显然不会永远在这里
that's our ShaderDataType, so what I'm gonna do is write a function up here, that's obviously not gonna live here forever
它会被调用，我们会让它返回，我们会让它返回一个GLenum，我猜就是那个类型
it's gonna be called, we'll have it return a, we'll have it return a GLenum, which is what that type I guess
prime的VertexAttribPointer实际期望的类型是什么
what the VertexAttribPointer of prime would actually expect the type to be
我们会看到ShaderDataTypeToOpenGLBaseType
we'll see ShaderDataTypeToOpenGLBaseType
以防在ShaderDataType到OpenGL基类型之间有一个转换
in case there's going to be a conversion between the ShaderDataType to the OpenGL base type
同样，我们会有一个关于类型的switch语句
so again, we'll have a switch statement on type
哦，我的天，为我做了这些，那很酷，可能现在要做所有的事情，我不打算这样做
oh my gosh, did that for me, that's pretty cool, might actually have to do all of it now, I wasn't planning to
这是我计划的一次，实际上没有做所有这些，但我想我现在必须做了，所以在这种情况下
this is the one, this is the one time I was planning on, not actually doing all of these, but I guess I will have to now, so in this case
我们会返回GL_FLOAT，那实际上会是这样，我想对于很多这些来说，包括这个
you know, we're gonna just return GL_FLOAT, and that's actually gonna be the case, I think for a lot of these, so this included
对吧，你们并不总是需要这个函数，但有时确实需要它
right, and you you don't always need this function, but you do sometimes need it
我想对于那个，对于那个，它很好，所以这就是GL_INT
and I guess for that, for that, it's fine, so this is GL_INT
我们还没有处理unsigned int，但是你们知道，如果以后真的需要它，那么可以这样做
and we haven't dealt with unsigned int, but you know, if we really want that in the future, then we can just do that in the future
好吧，我不知道，我们只会有GL_BOOL，我不知道，因为这不是我们整天做的事情
okay, I don't even know, we'll just have GL_BOOL I guess, I don't really know, because this isn't something that we do all day
所以未知就返回0，好了，酷，那么继续，现在我们要做的就是到这里
so unknown that returns 0, okay, cool, so there we go, so now what we can do is actually go here
看到我们有ShaderDataTypeToOpenGLBaseType，那就是我们如何输出GL_FLOAT
and see that we have ShaderDataTypeToOpenGLBaseType, and that's how we go out GL_FLOAT
现在它是否标准化了，这很容易做到，就是element.Normalized，我忘了标准化
now whether it's normalized, again really easy to do, element.Normalized, oh my gosh, I forgot about normalization, didn't I
Normalized，如果那是真的，那么我们就返回GL_TRUE
Normalized, so if that's true, then we'll do GL_TRUE
不管怎样，我忘了一些东西，否则就是GL_FALSE
anyway, I forgot something, otherwise GL_FALSE
好了，stride显然是layout，不是element，而是layout.Stride, GetStride
okay, the stride obviously is going to be layout, not element, but layout.Stride, GetStride
我以为我做到了，显然没有
I thought I did that, apparently not
偏移量是element.Offset，然后我们将它转换为一个const void*
and the offset is going to be element.Offset, okay, and we'll cast this to a const void pointer
好吧，有点难看，因为它太大了，但是我们有很长的代码行
alright, bit hard to see, because it's pretty big, but there we have our huge line of code
我应该把它分成几行，我想我会把它分成几行
which I probably should break into multiple lines, that I guess I will break it up into multiple lines
看看你们的人能看到所有的东西，所以我们会有所有这些东西
just see your guys can see all of it, so we'll kind of have all of this stuff
我猜每一个参数都在几行上，就像这样，好了
I guess every parameter on a several line, just like that, okay
和Normalized，所以需要加上这个，Buffer，bool Normalized，我也不知道，默认为false
and Normalized, so we need to add that, so Buffer, bool Normalized, which again like I don't know, we'll just have it as false by default
现在还没有真正的方法来设置它，但可能有构造函数，我的意思是，看，让我们友好一点
and no real way to set it for now, but we might have a constructor, I mean, look, let's just be nice
让我们看看bool，实际上我确定它都适用于初始化列表，但如果我们这样做，它是否有效
let's just see bool, well I'm actually sure it's all work with initializer lists, but if we just do that, does that work
这还是可以的，很酷，所以我们现在可以选择性地指定它是否标准化了，所以标准化对
yeah that still works, cool, so we can now optionally specify whether or not this is normalized, so normalization is good for
如果你们提供的是unsigned int类型，想让它自动转换成vec4类型或者浮点类型
if you're supplying like an unsigned int essentially, and you want it to automatically convert into a vec4 or like floats
它实际上可以那样做，你们只是看到，提供了一个int型，它需要被标准化
it can actually do that, you just see that, you're supplying an int, and that it needs to be normalized
你们就会得到那个，这个没有叫GetStride()的成员，所以你们现在能做的是
and you'll get that, this has no member called GetStride(), yeah so what you can do now is
如果要将某物标准化，你们可以做那个，对吧，再说一次，我不确定
if something were to be normalized, you could just do that, right, and again, not sure
所以这里你们不会做那个
yeah so you wouldn't do that here
但如果你们有颜色作为它的参数，可能会尝试一下，为什么不呢，我今天感觉有点冒险
but if you had like a color as it as an outside in, we might actually try that out, you know, why not, I'm feeling a bit adventurous today
我感觉我真的在做一些事情，尽管这期视频很长，不管怎样，我不讲了，那么就是GetStride
and I'm feeling like actually doing stuff, even though this video is dragging on, anyway, I'll stop talking, so GetStride
我们需要添加，所以我们有stride, inline uint32_t GetStride() const，返回m_Stride
we need to add that, so we have stride, inline uint32_t GetStride() const, return m_Stride
好了，我想就是那样，如果我按f5，现在应该可以运行了
alright, I think that's it, like if I hit f5, now it should probably work
我们试试，还没有设置layout，严格来说，不需要这样做，因为我们只是从这里读取
let's just try oh, and we haven't set layout, that's a, we don't have to, technically speaking, because we're just reading it from here
不管怎样，我们有一个？？？，好了，没有默认构造函数，所以需要添加默认构造函数
anyway, we have a capalar, okay, no default constructor, that's a good point, so we need to add default constructors for all of these
对吧，BufferElement，因为它们需要被初始化还有BufferLayout，现在你们可以不那么懒了
right, BufferElement, because they need to be initialized and BufferLayout, now you could be less lazy with this
实际上给你们的东西全参数，它在这里运行，在这里不运行，现在不麻烦了
and actually give your things to full parameters, it works for here, doesn't work for here, not gonna bother for now
好了，点击f5，看看会发生什么，好了，看我们有了三角形，多酷啊，真的很酷
okay, let's hit f5, and see what happens, okay, look at that we have our triangle, how cool is that, that's really cool
上次我们也做过，现在尝试添加一个颜色，我要做的是在我的布局中，添加一个新的Float4
we had that last time as well, let's try and actually add a color now, so what I'm gonna do is inside my layout, just add a new Float4
它将是我的颜色，然后我想进入着色器，并添加layout(location = 1) in vec4 a_Color;
it's going to be my color, and then I want to go into the shader, and add layout(location = 1) in vec4 a_Color;
好吧，我现在不打算用它，让我们看看它是否有用，对吧
okay, I'm not going to use it for now, let's just see if this even works, right
事实上，我甚至不需要在这里加上它，我们先把它拿出来，我可以把它从末端拿出来，这样我就可以撤销它了
in fact I don't even have to add it here, let's just keep that out for now, I might just take it out of the end, so I can undo it
但这里所有东西都可以，我们唯一需要的就是这里的所有东西，我们指定一种颜色
but everything should work here, the only thing we need is actually everything here, so let's specify a color
让我们把这个画成粉色，我想我们会看到1 0 1 1
let's just make this thing pink, I guess we'll see 1 0 1 1
对吧，有点粉色，洋红色，所以每个顶点都是那个颜色
right, that's kind of pink, magenta, so every vertex will be that color
然后我们可能一会儿就可以把它们相互作用，看看是什么样子，但现在我们先从粉色开始
and then we can probably interplay between them in a minute as well, just to see what that looks like, but for now we'll start with pink
这意味着我们现在每个顶点有7个元素，所有东西都应该自动计算
which means we now have, I guess 7 elements per vertex, everything should be calculated automatically though
那就是它的美妙之处，如果我们去掉这个，就会得到和上次一样的结果
that's the beauty of this, and if we take away this, we should just get exactly the same result this last time
尽管我们的顶点缓冲区里有更多的东西，希望其他的东西都不需要改变，看看那个
even though our vertex buffer has more stuff in it, hopefully everything else did not need changing, look at that
我们仍然得到三角形，即使顶点缓冲区不同，显然被破坏了，偏移量正常工作
we still get our triangle, even though our vertex buffer is different, clearly destroyed, and the offsets are working correctly
否则它不会，你们知道，它会把接下来的三个顶点读成这样，我们的三角形看起来就不一样了
otherwise it wouldn't, you know, it would read the next three vertices as being this, and our triangle would look different
让我们恢复颜色并在里面设置颜色，我们需要把这个给片段着色器
let's bring back the color and actually set the color inside, okay, so we need to give this to the fragment shader
所以我们就会看到，out vec4 v_Color，复制粘贴到这里，调用它，就是in vec4 v_Color
so we'll see, out vec4 v_Color, copy that, paste that here, call it, in vec4 v_Color
然后我们要设置color = v_Color，我在这里做这个，就在这个后面覆盖它，f5运行
and then we're going to set color equals v_Color, okay, I'll just do that over here, right after this one to override it, f5
我们得到了一个黑色三角形，这不是，对吧，那是因为我忘记设置颜色了
okay, so we get a black triangle, which isn't, right, that's because I forgot to actually set the color
很尴尬，你们可能认为我的缓冲布局代码不对，但实际上不是这样的
awkward right, you guys probably thought that my awesome buffer like layout code just wasn't right, but that's not actually
但它实际上是运行的，因为我已经重载了，所以我们有一个粉红色的三角形，很酷
yet it is actually in fact working, because I have roaded, so you know, all right, there we have a pink triangle, pretty cool
我要做的最后一件事就是改变颜色，这个顶点的颜色是粉色
last thing I'll do is actually just change the color, right, so the color of this vertex I leave is pink
这个顶点的颜色，我设为蓝色之类的，我把这个去掉，这些都是半色
the color of this vertex, I will set to like blue or something, so I'll get rid of this, and these are very half colors
显然，在这种情况下，我并不是想成为一个艺术家
obviously I'm not trying to be like an artist in this case
现在我猜他们中的一个可能喜欢黄色或其他东西
and now I guess what's that maybe one of them to like yellow or something
点击f5，看看会发生什么，现在我们已经定义了VertexBuffer
let's hit f5 and see what happens, okay, so now we have actually defined VertexBuffer
我们之前有粉色黄色和绿色蓝色，我不能，老实说，我不能提交这个代码
we have pink yellow and green blue before, I can't honestly, I can't commit this code
因为它看起来绝对是垃圾
because it just looks like absolute trash
所以我要做的是，我要让它看起来更好看，所以会看到0.8和0.2，这样就不会一直这么做
so what I'll do is make something, I'll make it just look nicer, so we'll see 0.8 and 0.2, just so that we're not kind of going all the way
实际上这需要是0.8，所以会看到0.8，我只是把颜色降低点，这样它们就不会那么刺眼了
actually this needs to be 0.8, so we'll see 0.8, I'm just scaling the colors down a little bit, so they're not as harsh
因为我真的很喜欢加一些其他的颜色，否则就像你们看到的那样，看起来很糟糕
because like honestly like and adding a bit more of other colors in, because otherwise like it just as you saw it, just looks so bad
我真的有点讨厌它，这样看起来会更好，如果我还没看到会发生什么，我们就点击
I really kind of hate it, this will make it look a lot nicer, so let's just hit, if I haven't seen what happens
我得把这句话印在t恤上，因为这显然是我最喜欢的现金短语了好吧，好了，真漂亮
I need to get that points on a t shirt, because apparently it's my favorite cash phrase ever ever, okay, beautiful
我们有了三角形，所有的测试都在运行，所有这些东西，你们知道的，布局都在正常运行
there we have our triangle with all of our test cars working, all of this stuff is now you know the layouts are all working correctly
显然，我们需要做的是把这个叫做SetLayout(layout)，我想我们能做的很酷
obviously what we actually need is to do is call this SetLayout layout, okay, and I guess what we can do just to be really cool
只是为了确保它能正常运行，只是为了确保我们从VertexBuffer中获得布局，这个不行吗
is just to make sure that works, is just to make sure that we kind of get the layout from the VertexBuffer, this is not gonna work
因为它显然是常数，我们不允许const，那很有趣，我们绝对应该，需要个构造函数来实现它
because it's constant apparently, and we don't allow Constance, that's fun, we definitely should, we need a constiturator to make that happen
我不知道，我认为那会运行的，但我猜不是，所以我猜我们还需要返回一个const_iterator
which I don't know, I thought that that would kind of just work, but I guess not, so I guess we need to also return a const_iterator
这是有趣的，const, const，是的，我想那应该可以了，好了，把它放在这里
which is you know fun, const, const, yeah I guess that that should work, okay, done, and I'll actually put that in here
为了确保我们不能访问那个布局，这个在我们说过之后就被销毁了
just to make sure that we can't even access that layout thing, so this actually gets destroyed in this case after we've said it
所以现在它应该从另一个东西开始
so now it should be started in the other thing
我猜很明显你们可能在把它放在这里之前把它带入一个变量
and I guess that obviously you probably brings that into a variable before putting it here
但为了好玩，我把它放在这里，让我们点击f5，看看会发生什么
but for fun, I'll just leave it here, let's hit f5 and see what happens
就是那样，那就是我的短语，一切都很好，漂亮
yep that's it, that's my phrase, everything works, beautiful
最后，为了让它看起来更漂亮，我将使用const auto& layout = that
and then finally just to clean it up and make it super nice, I'll just do auto const a reference layout equals that
我把这个放到这里，检查一下代码，现在它已经准备好提交了
and I'll just pop this in here, and just check that code, and then now it's like ready to commit
看起来很不错，好了，就是那样，那就是BufferLayout，我刚刚写的东西非常强大
and it will look nice, okay, that's it, so that is BufferLayout, this is very powerful what I've just written
对吧，就像这些东西真的很好，在你们的引擎中有这样一个系统真的很令人满意
right, like this stuff is really nice, really satisfying to have a system like this in your engine
因为这样你们就可以在脚本中做得很好，可以从视觉上看到布局
because that way you can just be really nice in the script, you can see that you can visually see layout
对吧，我看这里，我看到了什么
right, I look over here, what do I see
vec3 a_Position vec4 a_Color，float3 a_Position float4 a_Color
you know vec3 a_Position, vec4 a_Color, you know float3 a_Position, float4 a_Color
这里的所有东西都和这里显示的完全一样，这太神奇了，对吧，那就是你们想要的东西
everything's here in exactly the same way that it appears here, which is just amazing, right, that's the kind of stuff you want
你们不会想自己去做，比如摆弄数字，计算步幅，做所有那些事情
you don't want to be doing, like fiddling with numbers, working out strides, doing all that stuff yourself
不，你们这样描述你们的数据，这对DirectX来说是可以接受的
no, you describe your data in this way, it's going to be acceptable for DirectX
它会被OpenGL接受，一切都会正常运行，它会很漂亮，你们知道，如果你们做了一个
it's going to be acceptable for OpenGL, everything's going to work, it's going to be beautiful, and you know, if you make a
如果你们犯了这样的错误，就会清楚看到，这是不同的，对吧，就会看到，那是如何运行的
if you make a mistake like this, you know, you are look clearly, it's different, right, and that will you can see, kind of how that works
所以这就是我用优美的代码写出来的想法有点像那篇英语文章
so this is kind of the idea of what I was getting out with nice elegant code kind of like that English essay
希望那是有意义的，我希望你们能从中学到一些东西
hopefully that makes sense, and I hope that you guys can learn something from this
下次我还是想把这个移动到VertexArray，然后是这个东西
now next time again I do want to move this into VertexArray, and then this actual stuff, this actually
实际上就像找这些VertexAttribPointer，它会在OpenGLVertexArray中，就像你们知道的类
this actually like figuring out these VertexAttribPointer, that will be in the OpenGLVertexArray, like you know class
总之，我希望你们喜欢这期视频，如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧
so that'll be all kind of done through there, anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did, hit a like button
你们也可以访问patreon.com/thecherno来支持这个系列
you help support the series by going over the patreon.com/thecherno
如果喜欢那期，请帮助支持这个系列
please help support this series, if you liked that episode
因为所有这些人的支持使这些事情成为可能，现在如果你们想跳过，看看我写的东西
because all the support from all those people is what makes this kind of stuff possible, now if you do want to skip ahead and see what I've written
我有一个完整的PBR渲染，我已经展示了几次，可能会做一期视频
and I've got like a full PBR render, I've shown it off a few times, probably will make a video
比如在这周的某个时候展示一下，但如果你们现在就想访问源代码
like specifically showing it off sometime this week maybe, but if you want access to that source code just right now
今天你们可以去patreon.com/thecherno，它帮助你们了解系列，就会得到那个
today you can just go ahead and go to patreon.com/thecherno, it helps about series, and you will get access to that
现在告诉我你们的想法，对于整个BufferLayout的想法，我很喜欢这种处理方式
now let me know what you thought, what you thought of this whole kind of BufferLayout, I quite like this way of dealing with it
我可能都不喜欢，或者我觉得可能没有更好的办法了，他们会这么做的
I probably wouldn't even like gun in, or I feel like there's probably no better way, they're gonna do this
除非你们实际上，我不知道，这很奇怪，你们能做的显然是传递着色器
unless you actually, maybe I'm like, I don't know, it's be weird, what you could do is obviously pass the shader
然后再看看贴图的原因它们是有联系的
and then just figure out what it is cause in drug tax they're linked, anyway
但如果你们传递shader，你们就会知道你们的属性到底是什么
but if you pass the shader, and you just kind of figure out what your attributes actually are
然后你们自动设置并验证缓冲区布局，也许那样会更健壮，因为那样
and then you automatically set and validate the buffer layout like that, maybe that would be even more robust, because that way
没有代码复制，并且布局将从着色器自动计算出来
there be 0 Codeplication, and the layout would be automatically figured out from the shader
但除了做这样的事情，我觉得没有必要，说实话，你们得到了这些东西
but aside from doing stuff like this, I don't feel like that's necessary, to be honest, you get this stuff
对吧，你们就可以有一个VertexBuffer，分享到布局，一切都可以正常运行
right, and you can have a VertexBuffer, and your share to kind of layout correctly, and everything you should just work
所以请在下面的评论区告诉我你们的想法，希望我教会了你们一些新东西
so let me know what you what you thought in the comment section below, hopefully I taught you guys something new
这样你们就能写出更优雅的代码了，那是我的希望，但不管怎样，下次，就是VertexArray
and you kind of are now able to just write more elegant code, that's my hope, but anyway, next time, as I said VertexArray
我们想继续下去，把今天在Application类中写的一些代码移到顶点数组中
we want to kind of get on with that, and actually move some of this code that we've written here today in the Application class into vertex arrays
如你所见，外面很黑，因为它已经持续了这么长时间，下次见，拜
as you can see, it's dark outside, because that's how long its episodes been going for, I will see you next time, goodbye